A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, S-Z FA394
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Tennant, Mary Elizabeth
  - 1948, Tennant, Mary Elizabeth; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division (Reel M Ten 4, Frame 15, Box 466)
    The diary is arranged according to interview and visit and documents Mary Tennant's talks with professionals in the field of public health. The focus of the International Health Division in which Mary Tennant is a staff member is disease prevention and investigation of diseases important to public health. Tennant travels to South America to survey public health programs, facilities and infrastructure. She is also involved the selection of nursing fellows and discusses Rockefeller Foundation schools of nursing and public health education programs.
    Nursing; Medical education; Venezuela; Tuberculosis; Venereal diseases; Public health; United States; Colombia; Canada; Hygiene; Communicable diseases
  - Index, 1949
  - 1949, Tennant, Mary Elizabeth; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division (Box 466, Reel M Ten 4, Frame 201)
    The diary is arranged according to interview and visit and documents Mary Tennant's talks with professionals in the field of public health. The focus of the International Health Division in which Mary Tennant is a staff member is disease prevention and investigation of diseases important to public health. Tennant travels to Europe and South America to survey public health programs, facilities and infrastructure. She attends various public health conferences and receives updates on Rockefeller Foundation nursing fellows. The diary includes, "Study on the Schools of Nursing in Latin America."
    Panama; France; Hygiene; Medical education; Nursing; Costa Rica; Denmark; England; Finland; Belgium; Canada; Colombia; Communicable diseases; Sweden; Switzerland; Public health; Scotland; Tuberculosis; United States
  - Index, 1950; Tennant, Mary Elizabeth; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division (Box 466, Reel M Ten 4, Frame 361)
  - 1950, Tennant, Mary Elizabeth; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division (Box 466, Reel M Ten 4, Frame 375)
    The diary is arranged according to interview and visit and documents Mary Tennant's talks with professionals in the field of public health. The focus of the International Health Division in which Mary Tennant is a staff member is disease prevention and investigation of diseases important to public health. Tennant travels to India to survey nursing education. She also travels to Iran to survey the region for collaboration with the Rockefeller Foundation to development a comprehensive nursing program. She is updated with the present status of nursing fellows as well.
    Canada; Chile; Nursing; Argentina; Psychiatry; Peru; Sanitation; Public health; Switzerland; Sri Lanka; United States; Tuberculosis; Venezuela; Uruguay; Mental health; Medical education; India; Hygiene; Italy; Iran; Communicable diseases; Colombia; Egypt; Ecuador
  - Index, 1951; Tennant, Mary Elizabeth; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division (Reel M Ten 4, Frame 589, Box 466)
    19 pages. Includes 1951 visits indexed by country.
  - 1951, Tennant, Mary Elizabeth; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division (Box 466, Reel M Ten 4, Frame 608)
    The diary is arranged according to interview and visit and documents Mary Tennant's talks with professionals in the field of public health. The diary includes "Proposals for expanded teaching Program at the Yale University School of Nursing ", the family study and information on Gilman Nursing Fellowship candidates.
    Psychiatry; Public health; Nursing; Mexico; Mental health; Hygiene; Guatemala; Germany; France; England; Denmark; Canada; Belgium; Sweden; Switzerland; Tuberculosis; United States
  - 1952, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Medicine and Public Health; Tennant, Mary Elizabeth (Box 466, Reel M Ten 4, Frame 828)
    The diary is arranged according to interview and visit and documents Mary Tennant's talks with professionals in the field of public health. The diary details the Rockefeller Foundation collaboration with the University of Heidelberg's School of Nursing, the Family Study, the Soissons project, and reports on nursing in Italy.
    Finland; France; Germany; Italy; Medical education; Norway; Nursing; Portugal; Tuberculosis; Switzerland; Sweden; Scotland; Belgium; Communicable diseases; Denmark; England; Public health
  - Visits, 1953; Tennant, Mary Elizabeth; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Medicine and Public Health (Box 467, Reel M Ten 5, Frame 1)
    Index by country.
  - Index, 1953; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Medicine and Public Health; Tennant, Mary Elizabeth (Reel M Ten 5, Frame 4, Box 467)
  - 1953, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Medicine and Public Health; Tennant, Mary Elizabeth (Box 467, Reel M Ten 5, Frame 22)
    The diary is arranged according to interview and visit and documents Mary Tennant's talks with professionals in the field of public health. The Division of Medicine and Public Health mission is focused on the development of local institutions for the training of personnel and prosecution of research in the field of public health.
    Nursing; Netherlands; Public health; Portugal; Spain; Serbia; United States; Switzerland; Austria; France; England; Medical education; Germany
  - Visits, 1954; Tennant, Mary Elizabeth; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Medicine and Public Health (Box 467, Reel M Ten 5, Frame 254)
    Visits made in 1954; Indexed by country.
  - Index, 1954; Tennant, Mary Elizabeth; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Medicine and Public Health (Box 467, Reel M Ten 5, Frame 258)
  - 1 January 1954 - August 1955, Tennant, Mary Elizabeth; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Medicine and Public Health (Box 467, Reel M Ten 5, Frame 278)
    The diary is arranged according to interview and visit and documents Mary Tennant's talks with professionals in the field of public health. The Division of Medicine and Public Health mission is focused on the development of local institutions for the training of personnel and prosecution of research in the field of public health. The diary includes statistics concerning collegiate nursing education.
    Mexico; Norway; Italy; Medical education; Portugal; Public health; Nursing; Peru; Colombia; Canada; Ecuador; Denmark; Argentina; Hospitals; Brazil; Belgium; Germany; Greece; United States; Uruguay; El Salvador; England; Finland; France; Sweden; Scotland; Switzerland
- Thompson, Kenneth W.
  Biographical / Historical
  Kenneth Winfred Thompson was a pioneering international relations scholar with a long and varied career in philanthropy and higher education. He spent more than two decades working for the Rockefeller Foundation (RF), rising through the ranks of the Social Sciences Division and into the role of vice president.
  Thompson was born on August 29, 1921, in Des Moines, Iowa. He completed his B.A. in history (1943) at Augustana College in Sioux Falls, South Dakota, and served in the U.S. Army in infantry and military intelligence during World War II. He went on to earn his M.A. (1948) and Ph.D. (1950) in political science and international relations at the University of Chicago.
  Thompson began his career in academia, first as an Assistant Professor of Political Science at the University of Chicago, and then as an Associate Professor and Chairman of the International Relations Committee at Northwestern University. He began working for the Rockefeller Foundation in 1953 as a consultant in International Relations, and left his position at Northwestern University in 1955 to become the Foundation's assistant director for Social Sciences. He quickly earned promotions within the RF, becoming associate director for Social Sciences in 1957, director of Social Sciences in 1960, and vice president in 1961.
  As a scholar, Thompson was an influential theorist of international relations; as a Rockefeller Foundation officer, he worked tirelessly to foster the development of the international relations discipline. Thompson organized and nurtured the Foundation's International Relations Program (IRP), which began informally in 1955 with grants-in-aid for early career scholars in the emerging discipline. With Thompson's persistence, the program was formally established in December 1960 to provide grants to individual scholars researching foreign policy, diplomatic history, and international relations theory. The IRP was modeled on an earlier Foundation initiative, the Legal and Political Philosophy (LAPP) program. As with the IRP, Thompson's ability to foster and promote exciting new scholarship played a critical role in the LAPP program's success. Notable grantees included Hannah Arendt, Zbigniew Brzezinski, George F. Kennan, John Rawls, H. J. Morgenthau, Leo Strauss, and Reinhold Niebuhr.
  Thompson remained an active scholar during his years at the Rockefeller Foundation. He held endowed lectureships at New York City's Riverside Church (1958), Duke University (1959), and New York University (1962), and authored several books including Christian Ethics and the Dilemmas of Foreign Policy (1959), Political Realism and the Crisis of World Politics (1960), American Diplomacy and Emergent Patterns (1962), and The Moral Issue in Statecraft (1966). A 1961 Rockefeller Foundation profile observed that Thompson "continued his work in the field as a scholar and speaker at a rate that, even by those whose only profession is scholarship, must be considered just slightly this side of awesome."
  Thompson is perhaps best known for the third phase of his career, after leaving the RF in 1974. Thompson resumed his academic career as a professor of government and foreign affairs at the University of Virginia. In 1978, he became Director of UVA's Miller Center of Public Affairs, a nonpartisan institute devoted to the study of the presidency and political history. He played an integral role in creating the Center's Presidential Oral History Program and the Forum Program speaker series, and he held this position until his retirement in 1998. Over the course of his career, Thompson wrote and edited more than forty books and countless articles about international relations, foreign policy, diplomacy, and presidential history.
  Kenneth Thompson died in February 2013 at the age of 91.
  - 1953 (Box 468)
  - 1954 January-April (Box 468)
  - 1954 May-September (Box 468)
  - 1954 October-December (Box 468)
  - 1955 January-March (Box 468)
  - 1955 April-June (Box 468)
  - 1955 July-October (Box 468)
  - 1955 November-December (Box 468)
  - 1956 January-March (Box 469)
  - 1956 April-June (Box 469)
  - 1956 July-October (Box 469)
  - 1956 November-December (Box 469)
  - 1957 January-June (Box 469)
  - 1957 July-December (Box 469)
  - 1958 January-July (Box 470)
  - 1958 August-December (Box 470)
  - 1959 January-March (Box 470)
  - 1959 April-May (Box 470)
  - 1959 June-September (Box 470)
  - 1959 October-December (Box 470)
  - 1960 January-February (Box 471)
  - 1960 March (Box 471)
  - 1960 April (Box 471)
  - 1960 May-July (Box 471)
  - 1960 August (Box 471)
  - 1960 September (Box 471)
  - 1960 October (Box 471)
  - 1960 November-December (Box 471)
  - 1961 January-February (Box 472)
  - 1961 March-April (Box 472)
  - 1961 May-June (Box 472)
  - 1961 July-September (Box 472)
  - 1961 October-December (Box 472)
  - 1962 January-April (Box 473)
  - 1962 May-June (Box 473)
  - 1962 July-December (Box 473)
  - 1963 January (Box 473)
  - 1963 February-June (Box 473)
  - 1963 July-December (Box 473)
  - 1964 January-February (Box 474)
  - 1964 March-July (Box 474)
  - 1964 August-December (Box 474)
  - 1965 January-May (Box 474)
  - 1965 June-September (Box 474)
  - 1965 October-December (Box 474)
  - 1966 January-June (Box 475)
  - 1966 July-December (Box 475)
  - 1967 January-July (Box 475)
  - 1967 August-December (Box 475)
  - 1968 January-June (Box 475)
  - 1968 July-December (Box 476)
  - 1969 (Box 476)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 476)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 477)
  - Index (Box 477)
- Tisdale, Wilbur E.
  - 1926 December 7-1927 December 15 (Box 478)
    With E. W. Lindstrom.
  - 1928 January 15-April 24 (Box 478)
  - 1928 May 24-1929 January 1 (Box 478)
    With E. W. Lindstrom and W. J. Robbins.
  - Log 3, 1929 April-October (Box 478)
  - 1930 (Box 478)
  - 1931 (Box 478)
  - 1932-1933 (Box 479)
  - 1934-1935 (Box 479)
  - 1936 (Box 479)
  - 1937 (Box 479)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 479)
- Todaro, Michael P.
  - 1970-1971 (Box 480)
  - 1972-1974 (Box 480)
- Towne, D. H.
  - 1963-1964 (Box 480)
- Trant, Gerald I.
  - 1967 (Box 480)
- Trapido, Harold
  Sardinia (Italy)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 480)
- Unrau, Gladwin Olin
  - 1965 (Box 481)
  - 1966 January-1967 January 7 (Box 481)
  - 1967 January 8-1969 December (Box 481)
  - 1970-1974, 1977 (Box 481)
- Upatham, Edward S.
  - 1968-1974 (Box 481)
- Van Sickle, John V.
  - 1929-1930 (Box 482)
  - 1931 (Box 482)
    Kittredge was born in 1891 and died in 1957.
    With Tracy B. Kittredge
  - 1934-1938 (Box 482)
- Vavich, Mitchell T.
  - 1966-1967 (Box 483)
- Veenstra, John Gerald
  - 1965 (Box 483)
- Velazquez, Gabriel P.
  - 1972-1977 (Box 483)
- Vincent, George E.
  George E. Vincent, second president of the Rockefeller Foundation (RF), was born in 1864 in Rockford, Illinois.
  He received his B.A. from Yale University in 1885. Following graduation, he worked for the Chautauqua Institution which provided flexible adult education courses and home study programs for adults. The Chautauqua movement was initiated in New York by George Vincent's father, Methodist Bishop John H. Vincent.
  In 1892 Vincent began work as a graduate student in the sociology department at the University of Chicago. While there, he and department chair, Albion Small co-authored Introduction to the Study of Sociology, the first sociology textbook to be published in the U.S. Vincent completed his dissertation, "Social Mind and Education," and received his Ph.D. in 1896. He remained at the University of Chicago as a teaching fellow and attained a full professorship in sociology in 1904. He later served as dean of the Junior College and the College of Arts, Literature and Sciences.
  In 1911 Vincent accepted a position as president of the University of Minnesota, where he spent the next six years cementing the University"s reputation as a major research institution. Vincent also created the University's Extension Division for adult education and helped to create a partnership between the medical school and the Mayo Foundation.
  In 1917 Vincent was named president of the RF, a post he held for twelve years. As president he supported the continued expansion of the RF's public health activities, including the creation of the RF's Division of Medical Education, which was responsible for improving medical education outside of the U.S. Vincent also initiated programs in the natural sciences and oversaw a major reorganization of the Foundation into five divisions in 1928. In addition to his role as RF President and Trustee, Vincent was a member of the General Education Board (GEB), Peking Union Medical College (PUMC) and the China Medical Board (CMB).
  Throughout his career Vincent remained a member of the American Sociological Society, which he helped found in 1895, and also contributed his time as an editor of the American Journal of Sociology.
  George E. Vincent passed away in February of 1941 after a lifetime of influential work in the fields of education, sociology, and philanthropy.
  - Index, 1917; Rockefeller Foundation; Vincent, George E. (George Edgar) (Reel M Vin 1, Frame 20, Box 484)
    1917 Index; 4 pages
  - 1917, General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board; Vincent, George E. (George Edgar); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Rockefeller Foundation (Box 484, Reel M Vin 1, Frame 24)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Vincent talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As President of the Rockefeller Foundation he steers the focus toward supporting the war effort and making the world a better place through public health funding. The 1917 diary includes the China Medical Board developing a comprehensive medical system in China, the International Health Board focusing on preventive medicine, and camp and community plans for the welfare of American soldiers. Includes Memorandum to Members of the Executive Committee. Washington Interviews, May 26, 1917; and Memorandum of an interview with M. Hovelacque, A Member of the French Commission, at the Plaza Hotel, Made Tuesday, May 29, 1917.
    Canada; Nursing; Military training camps; Medical education; Malaria; Libraries; World War I; Hygiene; United States; Europe; Tuberculosis; China; Public health; American Red Cross; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Peking. Union Medical College
  - Index, 1918; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board; Vincent, George E. (George Edgar) (Box 484, Reel M Vin 1, Frame 145)
    1918 Index; 5 pages
    Drug addiciton; Hookworm disease; Medical education; Malaria; Influenza; Hygiene; Public health; Nutrition; Nursing; Military training camps; World War I; United States; Tuberculosis; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); American Red Cross; Peking. Union Medical College
  - 1918, General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Vincent, George E. (George Edgar); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board (Box 484, Reel M Vin 1, Frame 150)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Vincent talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As President of the Rockefeller Foundation he steers the focus toward supporting the war effort and making the world a better place through public health funding. The 1918 diary documents Vincent overseeing and getting updates on Rockefeller Foundation projects from various other officers. A focus of this diary is the war effort particularly concerning war camps. Includes: Memorandum of a Conference Held at 61 Broadway, monday Afternoon March 25, 1918 at 3pm.
    World War I; United States; Nursing; Military training camps; Tuberculosis; Nutrition; Influenza; Hygiene; Medical education; Malaria; Hookworm disease; Drug addiciton; Peking. Union Medical College; American Red Cross; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
  - Index, 1919; Rockefeller Foundation; Vincent, George E. (George Edgar) (Reel M Vin 1, Frame 269, Box 484)
    1919 Index; 5 pages
  - 1919, Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board; Vincent, George E. (George Edgar); General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board (Reel M Vin 1, Frame 274, Box 484)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Vincent talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As President of the Rockefeller Foundation he steers the focus toward supporting the war effort and making the world a better place through public health funding. The 1919 diary documents Vincent overseeing and getting updates on Rockefeller Foundation projects from various other officers, compiling of a hookworm bibliography, and a trip to the Far East to survey and tour medical education and public health facilities in Asia. He oversees construction of Peking Union Medical College.
    Canada; Hookworm disease; China; Hygiene; Hospitals; Japan; Industrial hygiene; Medical education; Korea; Public health; Nursing; United States; Tuberculosis; American Red Cross; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Peking. Union Medical College
  - Index, 1920; Rockefeller Foundation; Vincent, George E. (George Edgar) (Box 484, Reel M Vin 1, Frame 472)
    1920 Index; 6 pages
  - 1920, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Vincent, George E. (George Edgar); Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board (Reel M Vin 1, Frame 478, Box 484)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Vincent talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As President of the Rockefeller Foundation he handles the institutional and administrative duties of the Rockefeller Foundation, International Health Board and China Medical Board. The 1920 diary documents Vincent's trip to Canada to oversee and start the Canadian medical education program, further discussions of Peking Union Medical College, and its disease research and preventive programs in tuberculous and yellow fever.
    Canada; Yellow fever; United States; Tuberculosis; Public health; Medical education; Peking. Union Medical College; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
  - Index, 1921; Vincent, George E. (George Edgar); Rockefeller Foundation (Reel M Vin 1, Frame 664, Box 484)
    1921 Index; 5 pages
  - 1921, Rockefeller Foundation; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board; Vincent, George E. (George Edgar) (Reel M Vin 1, Frame 674, Box 484)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Vincent talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As President of the Rockefeller Foundation he is involved in the institutional and administrative duties of the Rockefeller Foundation, International Health Board and China Medical Board. The 1921 diary documents surveying and promotion of medical education in Europe and Asia and the formal opening of Peking Union Medical College.
    United States; Public health; Medical education; Korea; France; England; China; Belgium; Peking. Union Medical College
  - Exhibits, 1921; Rockefeller Foundation; Vincent, George E. (George Edgar); General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board (Box 484)
    Includes: Conference at Gedney Farms Hotel, White Plains, NY; Interviews with Staff Members; Engagements; Memorandum of Conference with President George B. Cuffen, Acadia University, Wolfville, NS; Visit to Art Center, 65-67 East 56 Street, NY; Memorandum on South Manchuria Railway; Memorandum on Plan of Inviting a Group of Japanese Medical Men to United States.
    Medical education; Public health; Peking. Union Medical College
  - Index, 1922; Vincent, George E. (George Edgar); Rockefeller Foundation (Reel M Vin 1, Frame 848, Box 485)
    1922 Index; 6 pages
    Scotland; Switzerland; United States; Canada; England; France; Hygiene; Medical education; Nursing; Public health
  - 1922, Vincent, George E. (George Edgar); Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board; Rockefeller Foundation (Reel M Vin 1, Frame 854, Box 485)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Vincent talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. As President of the Rockefeller Foundation he is involved in the institutional and administrative duties of the Rockefeller Foundation, International Health Board and China Medical Board. The 1922 diary documents surveying, promoting and creating public health medical education in Europe and America. He recieves status updates on current Rockefeller Foundation projects from officers. The diary includes: Confidential Memorandum regarding the University situation in Washington.